<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Aniket Handa</title><link href="http://blog.atneik.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://blog.atneik.com/feeds/studio.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://blog.atneik.com/</id><updated>2014-01-25T21:15:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Model Prototyping: Hand Blender</title><link href="http://blog.atneik.com/model-prototyping-hand-blender.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-25T21:15:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Aniket Handa</name></author><id>tag:blog.atneik.com,2014-01-25:model-prototyping-hand-blender.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This report presents the design and user testing while Model Prototyping a Handheld immersion blender. It was a weeklong project with focus on thinking with hands and in 3D. The product, i.e. the hand blender, needs to be developed for OXO brand, who are known for practicing universal design principles. The design of the prototype tries to adhere to the identity of the brand. The first section explains about constrains and the problem. The next section deals with designing of three separate prototypes of the product. The forth section showcases the prototypes. Finally, the report ends with an analysis and learning outcomes of the project.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Life is too short for bad design”. A badly designed tool can result in injury, be unusable, be unfit for a range of audience, etc. OXO have been designing tools for cooking and food preparation by keeping the user in centre and coming up with products that can be universally used and appreciated. Now, they wish to diversify by incorporating new technology with their well-known easy to use tools in a handheld immersion hand blender. Next section describes constrains of the design problem as derived from OXO’s principles and for well functioning of the product. The project focuses on characteristics such as ergonomics, easy to hold, fits everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Design Considerations &amp;amp; Constrains&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ergonomic &amp;amp; Universal design: As OXO follows universal design for developing products, which can fit quite large number of population. The product should be applicable to large audience; esp. considering extreme users such as with disabilities or a chef who uses it for long period of time and it should even be easy enough for casual users. Also, the product should be quite comfortable to be used for extended period of time. It should also not cause any injury while using it. This is the reason the prototypes are designed in accordance to fit most human hands and give support to specific portions of hand to minimise stress.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good Grips: The Good Grip series of the OXO brand boasts about large rubberised grips with serrated sides which provides confortable grip and confidence to a large number of people. Therefore, the three prototypes have large handles, which covers most portions of a hand and provides a secure grip. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Left/Right handed: Both left-handed and right-handed users should be able to comfortably use the product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usage: Here usage means that the user should be able to grab the blender by multiple positions. Moreover it should be intuitive enough to hold it correctly. While testing, it came to notice that some users prefer pressing the button using thumb and rest using index or middle finger. The prototypes consider that it should be comfortable to hold from multiple positions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safe: One of the prime things to keep in mind is safety of the device. Varied people in varied context would use the device. One such feature that all prototypes present is that of a ‘push button’ instead of two ‘on’ and ‘off’ buttons. The blender only runs when the button is pressed. This way if the device is goes out of control it would stop, and not continue running.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Screen and Buttons placement: The screen should be visible when using the device and also the main button should be easily accessible to a large audience. The screen displays information about current speed of motor, current consistency or viscosity of the food being blended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reach &amp;amp; Immersion: Hand blenders are flexible and have more use cases than a normal standing blender. They create less mess as one can blend or chop in the same vessel. They can also be used when the pot is on the stove, due to mobility. They can even reach a glass bottom. For these reasons, it was kept in mind that the design should be portable and the arm of the blender should be thin in diameter in order to reach bottom of most vessels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change speed while running using single hand: One problem that I regularly face when I use a hand blender is that, one cannot change the speed of the motor while it is running without using a second hand. The prototypes presented place the speed selector button in such a manner that it is accessible even when a person is running the machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set consistency: The user should not only be able to see a consistency, but also set a desired value of consistency. Herein the user will be informed by a ‘beep’ when the set consistency is reached. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple: The OXO’s designs are simple and intuitive to masses. It is considered that user is not bombarded with buttons. Minimal interface with priority to the most common case of ‘just blending’ for an average user is given importance while designing the prototypes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weight: To mimic the weight of a hand blender clay is used. Centre of mass and more weight of the motor is considered by inserting iron mesh in the core of the prototypes. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dimensions: To fit in the motor all three prototypes have 2.5 inches diameter at the widest width. Two of the three prototypes are more than 12 inches in height.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Basic Functionality&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Main push button for running the motor.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All three prototypes posses an easy accessible push button to turning on the motor and start blending. The button can pressed either using fingers or using a thumb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed control.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All three prototypes have a variable speed control unit. It has been positioned in such a way that one can change the speed while running it using the same hand. This enables users to operate the device single-handedly. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Display.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The display shows the user primly two quantities. One is the current speed of the motor. Other is the current viscosity of the liquid being blended. The user can also set the viscosity and the device will alert the user using a ‘beep’ when that value of viscosity is reached. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Viscosity.&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User should be able to set viscosity. The device will alert the user when specified viscosity or consistency has been reached.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prototype&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before prototyping the model of a hand blender, I basically did three activities. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Firstly, read more about OXO. I researched about their design philosophy, inspected their current product line, watched video demo of the products. This gave me design principles, which were common and followed at OXO. Some of them are listed in above section. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then secondly, I researched the product. For this, I visited an electronic appliance store to see current market offerings. I watched some cookery videos online to see how a cook typically uses a hand blender. Having been using hand blenders for long, I was amazed to discover that people don’t use it like I do. I use my thumb to press the main button, but some people use their fingers to push to main button. This changes the ergonomics of the design. After this, I laid down some constrains and design principles that are mentioned in above section. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finally, I went to the drawing board to sketch some of the initial designs. After being satisfied with the first sketch I went to model the conception using clay. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/5.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/6.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/7.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prototype 1&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/8.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first prototype I developed unfortunately broke and I just have a single picture of it. It had a large grip and fitted my hand perfectly. But upon quick testing with more hands it was obvious that the grip needed to be slimmer in future prototypes. In this one I used a filled plastic as core. But then in future designs I used a wire mesh. Wire mesh allowed less bulky grip and gave me more freedom to sculpt it.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prototype 2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/9.jpg" /&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second prototype was slimmer than the first one at grip, but big enough to be following OXO’s Good Grip product line. Its usage was focused upon pressing the main button by thumb. The thumb intuitively fitted around the portion for push button. It was comfortable using by either left or right hand. There was embossment at the top of the design, this was to distribute the weight to the fingers. Also, it had support for the palm. One can set the viscosity using the scroll so that the device alerts user when certain consistency is reached. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/10.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/11.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/12.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/13.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prototype 3&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/14.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with the earlier prototype was that it was focused upon users who uses thumb to press the main button. In this next version The button was placed is such a manner that it could easily be controlled using fingers or using a thumb. The other dynamics of the prototype, such as the support and contours matched either side of griping case. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/15.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/16.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/17.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/18.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prototype 4&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/19.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The forth and the last prototype tried to combine the push button for running the motor and the speed control into one. The ball supports one axis movement for setting the speed. The same ball could be pushed to run the motor. For turbo mode it has a button in the front. The display is located at the top. Both left and right-handed users can use it comfortably. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/20.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/21.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/22.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the whole Family together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W3/23.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Improvements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototypes were evolved as the problems were discovered, but still keeping in mind the diversity of design. For example, the first prototype was too large for most hands therefore the size of the handle was reduced. The second design concentrated on users who press the main button by thumb. Then upon discovering that there are users who prefer to use fingers instead of thumb, the design was evolved. While designing all the prototypes constrains and principles listed in above sections where kept in mind and also discovered. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion &amp;amp; Critiques&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The testers appreciated the efforts to incorporate good ergonomics and universal design. But, they also criticised the lack of any colour or interface on the device. This was intentional, as I wanted to check the intuitiveness of the button by just feeling it. I didn’t wanted to give visual clues to the button and wanted to test that if the prototypes performed fine if the user is just touching/feeling the prototype. The focus of testing was on comfort, both handed and accessibility of buttons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case of 60-sec video, the audio was a problem. The volume was low, and not all could correctly understand what user tester was saying. Though, the video was commended for being simple and to the point.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="prototyping"></category></entry><entry><title>Model Prototyping an Eco ATM</title><link href="http://blog.atneik.com/model-prototyping-eco-atm.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-19T21:20:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Aniket Handa</name></author><id>tag:blog.atneik.com,2014-01-19:model-prototyping-eco-atm.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After paper prototyping last week, it was time for 3D. We were suppose to design and build a prototype of an EcoATM within 2 hours. For those who wonder what that is - its simply a mobile phone recycling box which give you some cash (not much) for your old phone. There were some basic functional requirements that need to be covered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A touch screen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A receipt and QR code printer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cash Dispenser&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt; compartment wherein user can deposit the phone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An ID Scanner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visual Scanner for detecting device condition, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some non-functional requirements that we considered:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gives sense of Security and Transparency &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ergonomics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before heading to the development board, we scratched our head for improving the current state of art. We identified some of the problems which we could address, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The screen placement wasn't for everyone. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The phone placing compartment was opaque. It gave a feeling of insecurity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The overall flow and processes was way too complex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discussing these issues we individually sketched some ideas. We spend a considerable time sketching, as compared to others, though in this particular exercise we suppose to think with hands. But, it was fruitful, we came with an ambitious and unique idea for implementing the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/11.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/13.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/25.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/18.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally this is what we build..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/19.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screen was the center of the design. We conceptualized it to have a camera to recognize faces and adjust according to there height. For this we made it in such a way it had two degrees of freedom, it rotated on the horizontal axis and went up and down. The user could place the phone on the screen when it was completely horizontal. The compartment was replaced by covering up the screen with a transparent cover after the phone was placed. The system can be better understood in action than by reading words (one of the reason to prototype). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/22.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We actually used Wizard of Oz technique to give the experience of using it. Here is a fun video..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="flex-video widescreen" style="margin: 0 auto;text-align:center;"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="100%" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/UtQZuLq0X5k?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I learned?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modeling promotes thinking on-the-fly. You're ideating about possible solutions while you're building stuff.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brings out possible issues with the design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Makes you feel &amp;amp; experience the product without much investment (two hours?).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's a great tool to better communicate ones idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's fun!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="prototyping"></category></entry><entry><title>Paper Prototyping: Wearable UIs</title><link href="http://blog.atneik.com/paper-prototyping-wearable-uis.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-19T21:15:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Aniket Handa</name></author><id>tag:blog.atneik.com,2014-01-19:paper-prototyping-wearable-uis.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Wearables are the future!”, as deemed by majority of futurist. Together with a smartphone they can provide altogether new experiences. Here we choose a Smartwatch as the wearable and try to understand the interplay between the two devices. The accessibility of a Smartwatch and low friction involved in using it can be exploited to provide omnipresent computing. This week long endeavour used the technique of paper prototyping to quickly iterate over various designs possible for a Fitness App. The App helps user create routines in a smartphone and then help them follow the same while working out though the smartwatch as a medium. The system is named Gym Mate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us use Internet to learn new things, and learning new exercises is done in a similar manner. But, the problem is that, it’s quite difficult to find an exercise on a smartphone and then use it to follow the exercise while at a Gym. Now imagine this for every exercise. Now this is where a smartwatch comes into picture, which can show animations of the exercise and also guide through the routine while being non intrusive. Watch can also help users keep track of resting time between two exercises. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also there is no way to record actual exercises done during a Gym session (except of course self logging, which has way too much friction). This two-device system can record history and then provide long-term benefits by showing visualizations of overall health on the phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Design Considerations &amp;amp; Constrains&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easy to sync: The interplay between the watch and a phone can easily become a headache and hard to understand. The phone application provides a single large button ‘Start’ when the routine is set to go. Upon pressing the button the routine is uploaded to the watch and a message is shown on both the devices. Here it assumes that the devices are already paired using Bluetooth or similar technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does not bombard user with options: The interaction promotes the user to follow the most common case and make things less complicated for an average user. Earlier versions of the application scheduled the routine weekly rather than just in time. This was making the system complicated and time intensive. Therefore, it was striped down to only create instant routines and upload it to the watch. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses the limited watch screen space efficiently: The main utility of the application is to show the animations of exercises. This needs space. So, sole focus was given to the animation with only a single button to inform termination of the exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fulfils current goal of the user: During user testing it became evident that users might not create schedules for a weeklong gym routine and rather create them on the fly. So, the system focused on users’ current goal of quickly manipulating the routine and uploading it to the watch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provides short-term and long-term value: Short-term goals are met by delivering animations so that user correctly performs the exercise. Also the Watch helps user on track by clearly showing the flow of the routine from resting time to &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Basic Functionality&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create instant Gym routines on phone by combining numerous Exercises.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transfer routine form the phone to the watch. Transfer actually completed exercises from the watch to the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Help user follow the routines (created on phone) using the watch with appropriate exercise animations and rest time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Visualize history of exercises done, calories burned, etc. according to week, month and year on the phone. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Prototype&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did three revisions of the design. Before achieving any fidelity, I first simulated the complete interaction using plain white cards. Within an hour, this activity revealed major flow problems in the design. It also gave me an idea what kind of interfacing elements would be needed to create the experience I have in mind. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/6.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The starting screen (when there is no routine) shows weekdays. The user is supposed to select a day and then add exercises to that particular day. This created the complete weekly schedule of the workout. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One the prime feature I wanted was an intuitive Timeline to represent the Routine in a form of a Scroll wherein users can easily edit the exercise by sliding them off to delete and adding them using a ‘+’ button. To give a proper experience of a scroll I created a phone using cardboard and made two slits, one at the top and other at bottom, so as to make paper slide through vertically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To select the exercise to be added to the routine, I created a checked list that the user could scroll and check the exercises he/she wanted in the routine, and then finally tap on done. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/9.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/8.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After addition of exercises the routine is ready to be uploaded to the watch. The upload is automatically done by tapping on ‘Start’ button. This shows a message ‘Your watch is ready is go’ on the phone. While simultaneously, the watch shows ready to Go!’. Now, tapping on ‘Go!’ begins the routine. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the watch side, it was simple and functional so as to better use the small screen. The watch that I prototyped was actually two times the scale of the original conception. This was to better support the interaction and the ease of creating. Now as the user tapped on ‘Go!’, the routine begins in the watch. The watch displays animations of the exercise and resting time in the same order the user specified in the routine. The watch at the end uploads the exercises (which user actually completed) to the phone to be archived in the history for future analysis. The watch also vibrates to alert the user at the end of each rest time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This second version was used for user testing. The tester was a Gym goer so could relate more to the application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally when the workout is finished the user can check his/her history of adherence to the routine. For this, the phone app shows charts/visualizations, according to week, month and year. These visualizations focus upon ‘How much user follows the routine?’, ‘Calories burned over the period?’, etc. All this data is possible as the watch syncs back the actual completed exercises to the phone. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/10.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After user testing and analysis I came up with the third version, which further improved some aspects of the prototype. The next section deals with analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Improvements&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first problem with the application was that, the application was difficult to grasp on the first usage. This was majorly due to weekly schedule instead of one single routine that the user can upload to the watch. To improve this, the application was simplified by just presenting a single routine instead every day of the week. Below is the new first screen of the application (if no routines). Upon addition of exercises the bottom button shows Start (as shown in above images).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another improvement was on the watch interface, wherein the status of the exercises was missing. The information about how many exercises are done and how many are left were not shown in the earlier version. This was elegantly implemented by showing a status bar on the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W2/5.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Conclusion &amp;amp; Critiques&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the testers and many other students appreciated the scroll functionality. Earlier versions had complains about being complex. This was due to considering weekly schedule instead of focusing upon current user needs. This was improvised in the third version of the application by uploading present-day routine rather than on weekly schedules. The complexity was further reduced by not showing all connection stages/states between the phone and the watch. It was assumed that both the devices are connected. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final version of the application worked well. It was self-explanatory and users spend less time figuring out the usage. The interaction was predictable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short 60-sec video of user testing was commended for editing and background sound, but it was regarded too fast to be able to concentrate on the interaction flow of the application (I 2xed it to show the complete interaction in 60-seconds limit). Signing off with the video..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="flex-video widescreen" style="margin: 0 auto;text-align:center;"&gt;
&lt;iframe width="100%" height="100%" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/MOZ3ZuVZ0nQ?rel=0&amp;controls=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;rel=0&amp;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="prototyping"></category></entry><entry><title>Paper Prototyping a Coffee Shop App</title><link href="http://blog.atneik.com/paper-prototyping-coffee-shop-app.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-01-13T10:20:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Aniket Handa</name></author><id>tag:blog.atneik.com,2014-01-13:paper-prototyping-coffee-shop-app.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This quarter is going to be exciting! As the Studio deals with the most waited phase of the process i.e. Prototyping. We start the first studio session by paper prototyping an Tablet App for ordering coffee at a Cafe. The project was narrowed to include only three kinds of coffee (Espresso, Macchiato and Cappuccino) coming in three different sizes. So, a total of nine offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W1/4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discussing the minimum requirements of the application; me and other team members started individually designing the layout and flow of the coffee application. We laid down some evaluation criterion using which we may evaluate our design. One of the most important ones being: &lt;em&gt;quickness&lt;/em&gt; (said frequently in the &lt;a href="http://blogs.uw.edu/hcid521/exercises#e1"&gt;exercise&lt;/a&gt;) or most less number of clicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used small white cards to draw the rough layout of the UI. Separate card for each manipulation possible helped me rapidly analyze and alter the flow of the interaction. In a relatively short time, I was able to discern that a single frame was enough to show all the desired information without back and forth between more frames. Dynamically changing the parameters and showing the final cost on same frame eliminated the need of more frames. Hence, making it a bit faster. This might have been possible due to low number of offerings. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While others came with, a nice top down layout of the elements (coffee on top and billing on bottom right) coherent with the visual flow followed by a typical user, and also with a robust way to represent billing information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then combined the best of our individual work to generate a single frame ready to be user tested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W1/2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple of user testing, the weaker sections of the design were clearly evident. First, was the ambiguous ‘Add’ button. Users clicked it add the order and got the feedback by lower half being updated. The problem was, how to remove an order? It wasn’t obvious. The other problem was the redundant billing information which was visually present on the upper half and numerically present in the lower half. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To solve these issues, we dropped the ‘Add’ button. And now any changes on the top updated the bill automatically. We provided feedback using text (like a &lt;em&gt;toast&lt;/em&gt; in Android OS). For the other issue we got rid of redundancy and now only showed cumulative sum of each kind of coffee along with total amount.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://dl.dropboxusercontent.com/u/23289062/siteImages/Studio/Q2/W1/3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made the flow improve tremendously. The user was now able to manipulate (increase or decrease) the total number of each offering needed in just two clicks. And then all that was required was to click on ‘Submit’ after reviewing the total amount. Adding tip was made easy by just tapping on some pre-calculated tipping percentages. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What I Learned?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Initial user testing are crucial. They reveal the most fundamental problems with the design.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make the most common case the fastest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show feedback and status.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If something is not clickable, blend it into the background. (here the coffee cups had a yellow background due to Post-it, so some users thought them as a Button)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Predictability over Smartness.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Think of all possible scenarios and permutations to break the system. :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rather than discussing in a team, try A/B testing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iterations. Iterations. Iterations. (rapid)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is this good/bad for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paper prototyping is a great way to quickly put down the ideas not only to test but also to communicate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remember not to put great efforts in visual aesthetics esp. initially. Its a fast and dirty way to fail ideas to move towards the quality ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Might not work for all kind of interfaces, such as 3D interfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even in touch interfaces it might not give the same experience for certain gesture based input methods such as swipe, slide, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="prototyping"></category></entry></feed>